I'm I'm here with Clive and Reiner. You
two have both come over to my house
often to talk about chips and hardware
software co-design, but for some reason
James Hill has decided to stick a camera
in our face this time.
Uh
yeah, introduce yourselves.
>> Yeah, I I I'm Reiner. I um I'm CEO of
Matics. Uh we we make chips for
uh large language models. Um and then
before that I was doing um
inference stack optimization at Google
for for all of this.
>> It's great to be here. Uh I'm a guy on X
that likes to talk about hardware and
software co-design.
>> Yes, I think I think like one of the
things you two have taught me a lot
about is just this this whole hardware
software design code space, right? So,
Reiner, you wrote the Palm paper, um and
I thought that was the best paper of
like '23. Uh maybe '22, I don't know
when it came out, but
>> We had to stop publishing after that.
>> Yeah, that was the last paper that
Google published that was like valuable
in infra.
Um
Yeah, and I thought that was super
interesting. And then and then Clive,
you you you know, you worked on a number
of really interesting things.
Um and you're co-designing for
completely different space before.
>> Yeah.
>> Um what is what does co-design mean?
>> So, co-design is when we can
uh not only make the software better
or the hardware better in isolation
given
just like
a fixed workload or a fixed piece of
hardware.
Uh we want to make both better, and so
we might want to
uh change the hardware in a way that
make some sacrifices today that will
reap rewards in the future once we
co-design for
that future hardware.
>> The thing that always confuses me is
like uh how
when you're doing co-design um
what exactly are you doing, right? Like,
you know, like it's like oh, are you
just changing the shapes of the map
moles, or like are you like what what
what what kind of optimizations even
exist in this space?
>> I mean, I think like
like the first thing is like the
sacrifices is the key point, right?
Like, uh what is a typical ML research
paper? It's
uh I've made some kind of my model
architecture um and therefore all the
metrics look better as a result. Like
that's the archetypical thing.
You can do that without code design.
That is just a model research. It
becomes code design when you say
actually some of these metrics are
getting worse,
but that's because these are metrics run
on the current generation of video GP.
And so
maybe I should look at a slightly more
generalized metric like what is the
the gate count of this of this
architecture or what is the energy cost
of this architecture or what's the
intelligence per picojoule
of this thing.
Um
And then so if you look at the more
generalized
metric, I think that sort of starts to
approach giving you the flexibility to
make all of the changes across the stack
rather than just localized to the
current generation of GPUs.
So I think like very simple things are
to take a case study. Like if you look
at the difference between a Swish
activation function,
evaluating Swish requires
evaluating some exponential functions.
Those require
function lookup tables, polynomial
approximations. There's a lot of
multipliers in them. Can be quite energy
intensive. At the other extreme is to
say ReLU is kind of the simplest
activation function at all.
Compared to greater than zero is
extremely simple to evaluate.
And so maybe it's cheaper in hardware to
do to use ReLU rather than Swish,
but maybe it's worse in in model
quality. And then now your question is
which one should I use? I want to do
that on the basis of mega
energy cost rather than rather than what
on systolic array on GP.
>> The example I love to give is
you can always make your systolic array
or tensor core wider in order to get
more arithmetic into one place.
But a lot of models are just not that
wide.
So
if you increase the the size of the
tensor core, you're not going to get any
faster execution of that model. But if
you
tell them, all researchers,
make the model wider. I know it's like
not completely efficient for ML, but
in net, once you also account for the
hardware efficiency gains,
it will be better.
>> Why don't masters do that? Like one
layer, uh 10 million wide or something
like that.
>> Well, if if you can build a 10 million
wide uh tensor core that can
run at the same power as a
uh
128-wide tensor core, then obviously
that's that's the right choice to make,
but
obviously that's not possible.
>> So so a bit of a philosophical question,
right? You see papers like um let's say
Deep Seek V3, their attention mechanism
was the first one at least of a public
paper where the arithmetic intensity was
equivalent to that of Hopper, right? In
terms of how many memory how much memory
bandwidth versus compute for the
attention mechanism. Um you look at
certain papers from other Chinese labs
where they're like
uh I think I think like Jen on Jen, I
don't remember which lab it was. It
might have been Alibaba, it might have
been someone else, but Jen on Jen, their
architecture was like very similar,
except they went from like 100 layers to
like 70 layers, and that just made
inference like 20% faster, right? Um are
these co-design because they're not
really influencing the hardware? They're
kind of looking at the hardware and the
confines that it has, and and then
making their model fit that hardware
really well.
>> Um I think a lot of people call a lot of
things co-design, uh but in
>> No true Scotsman is this that I be?
>> Yeah. I think in our in both of our
narrow views, uh co-design means that um
instead of designing your model
specifically for the hardware
capabilities, like Deep Seek has done
very well,
uh or designing your hardware for
uh models, which Nvidia's done very
well, you're looking at both of the same
time, and you're trading things off
where you might actually make a
sacrifice on model quality in order in
order to get much more efficient
hardware utilization, or the other way
around, uh such that end-to-end you're
doing better.
>> It it did It seems to be and maybe just
from the definition of it, uh you you
get hardware companies that do
co-design. Um
pure model companies maybe less so or,
you know, what's your read on that?
>> I mean,
you know, a public example is Trevor's I
posted a tweet uh screenshotting an
image of an email and that email was
like, "Hey, here's what we want for
hardware next to Nvidia." Yeah. Um and
Nvidia did implement many of these
things.
Um I don't know what amount, but they
did implement some of these things and
then they released GPT-5.3 codex. Um X
high is there are there more are there
more words after Is it just codex?
>> [laughter]
>> All the numbers.
>> Um anyways, you know, they released this
model and they say it's co-designed with
Blackbird. Is that Is that an example of
a model lab
with someone else's external hardware?
>> Yeah. Seems like it's a good example.
Um I think I think you do often kind of
get these ping-pong relationships where
you get feedback from from the model
designers and then the hardware
designers implement it. And then the
hardware comes back and then the model
designers get to take a look at it and
then feedback kind of ping-pongs back
and forth.
Uh but uh maybe the larger ambition
there is that we can look at both at the
same time.
>> How How do you How do you do that when
the ML researchers don't even know what
they're going to work on in like 6 to 9
months and you're like hardware time
cycles like I just The one I just
mentioned is 3 years.
>> Yeah, I mean, I would say like
hardware designers kind of have to have
to predict where the ML researchers are
going and like maybe take a um
kind of squint on what the ML
researchers are doing later. I I think
there's like
it's possible to look at trends for
sure. Recent trends, for example, seem
to have been um
hey look, Nvidia has a whole bunch of um
control resources at all of the ASNs.
Maybe we can figure out interesting ways
to use them and do something more
dynamic. So, like you can you can see
people how they're responding to trends.
I think long term you can't predict the
model is going to be exactly this shape.
That's hard to do.
Um but we're going to use more of the
resources that are available and less of
the ones that aren't is is a pretty
straightforward thing to predict, I
would say.
>> One of the things I've heard from
researchers and um is sort of
some of these chips that seem quite well
co-designed, right? Uh they actually
hate.
Um so an example is like a TPU V6E, uh
Trillium, I think is the public name.
Uh Ghost Light is the name that everyone
actually knows. Um but anyways,
it's very common for people from
DeepMind to be like, "Oh, this this chip
is really weird cuz it's got like a ter-
oh, sorry, a petaflop of compute and
like 32 gigs of HBM. It's like quite a
weird shape relative to the other chips
of the time, right? It's got like 1/4
HBM or something like that of a of a
Hopper and only half the flops. And if
you look at real utilizable flops, it's
it's like the same, right? It's it's
quite a weird chip. It makes sense in in
many contexts, but I guess a lot of
researchers hate it because it confines
where they can do the research. Is there
a way that co-design can go wrong?
>> I mean, I kind of think you want to make
a chip that people do hate to some
extent. Like uh the there's
people don't hate a chip if it's if it's
got a very wide um the basin uh of of
operating points where it can work in
well. Um and I think that actually means
you've left some resources on the table.
So, uh the like really you're looking
for
like you would like your model to use
all of the resources at 100% efficiency.
Um 100% utilization. Um
uh but if you can do that and sort of
leave some slack around, then maybe you
could have applied something. Often that
is make a memory smaller because your
batch size was too large. Or or if you
have multiple different ways to lay out
a model on on the chip, then um
then probably there would have been one
that was most efficient. Then the fact
you could do other ones um is a missed
opportunity. So,
I mean,
like I think it's a little glib to say
that uh you want to use this to hate
you, but uh but to some extent they
should work pretty hard to actually uh
get the most out of their hardware.
>> I mentioned like sort of one that's from
perhaps your history. Uh maybe one
that's also from perhaps your history is
like, you know, the the Dojo trips chips
RIP, right? Um sad sad they're uh
canceled and restarted maybe. I heard
restarted. Um
They they are also like really weird,
right? In terms of like
um
You know, I guess I guess it comes back
to my question of like do people hate
this, right? Is Is you know, they're
really really good at convolutional
neural networks.
Um there's like some really interesting
data locality stuff, but then like you
have no memory bandwidth, right? Like
it's pretty bad. Um
>> I mean, one of the one of the
interesting constraints of chips is that
they are two-dimensional. And you do
actually have to confront this fact
pretty actively when you're designing an
ML chip. Um and that's why
architectures like systolic arrays exist
that are very naturally suited to a
two-dimensional architecture, whereas
you also see architectures
um
many architectures that have like an L2
L1 cache that is
that wants to be connected to all the
different processors that are on the
chip. And that's maybe less suited to
uh embedding into 2D.
>> Mhm.
I guess but but in some way, right? Like
you know, Tesla's a huge buyer of GPUs,
right?
Um they continue every, you know, 6
months or so announce a big deal with
Nvidia.
Um of course they have their Dojo chips.
Um
So, we're going back to the whole point
of like you've constrained the user a
lot, right? Um
Maybe Dojo's not good at certain kinds
of model architectures, right? Uh is
does that slow down Is there Is there a
point where you co-design too much and
now all of a sudden like, you know,
you've left no flexibility on the table
and you know, you you've got you burned,
you know, the the architecture into the
silicon and like you end up with like
something that no one can use for modern
stuff because ML research is moving way
faster in different directions.
>> Yeah, that's the challenge is that you
have to
as a hardware designer kind of predict
the future. And you don't know where the
future is going to lead. I think the
most reliable way to think about this is
just like when you're doing ML research,
you are thinking about scaling loss and
you're thinking about what is the
how do I measure the direction that
things are going so that I can launch a
big run.
And then now we're thinking about in
terms of what is the direction things
are going so that I can design a chip
for
where the models will be.
>> And then the other thing you said is 2D,
which makes sense on a chip level.
Racks are three-dimensional though. So
there's there's a point where that
stops, right?
>> That's true.
>> Yeah.
>> You can definitely come up with some
very interesting network topologies in
in these racks.
There's the there's the torus for TPU
famously. There's
um
Nvidia has a I guess you would call it a
flattened butterfly?
>> Isn't it just switched all tall?
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> All sorts of fancy names for the same
thing. Um
Next generation TPUs have dragonflies.
>> That's interesting.
>> The traniums
I don't know what the hell you'd call
their architecture. It's like sort of a
torus and not only that it switches but
there's like switches in different trays
and like you can do all talls kind of
but like there's multiple it's weird. Um
It makes sense. It makes sense though
once you once you train up a model.
Yeah, I guess I guess
how does one like do you view it as just
a spectrum of like I'm over optimizing
for a problem or not or how much of this
is like the art of just like
you know
I would I think models will be there.
>> I mean I would say part of it is just
you're providing the raw materials. Um
you have to figure out like I mean
there's sort of a whole spectrum of
where you can provide these raw
materials. If you provide um ingredients
that are too small, like individual
gates, that's what an FPGA is, it's 10x
less efficient than an ASIC. So, don't
do that. Um
make the unit the grain size bigger. Um
like systolic array as the grain size.
Uh that's really pretty efficient for
that point. Um Uh and so, pick the grain
size appropriately. Um think about which
fusions should be in place and are
naturally there. So, maybe some
operations always get fused together,
and so you can have them as a bigger
grain size. Um and then just try and
expose those things uh
with as little overhead as possible. Um
so, I mean, that's sort of just like a
hardware-centric approach to it. It's
not really saying necessarily what are
the models uh wanting and predicting
what the models are, but it's just like
the you can bound your downside by doing
that. Like, I'm giving you all the
things, maybe I don't give you as much
of the things that I think you don't
need, but mostly I'm giving you the more
raw materials to work with. So, I think
that's a pretty safe hedge. Um
what you can do better than by taking
into
into account what you know about models
is say, "Well, actually, um
so, sure, we know that multiply and add
should always be fused together into
fused multiply add, uh but maybe I'll
know something about um attention
computations, and I can take advantage
of the fact that there's always a
softmax there, and I can do something
special for that, and so on." And so,
uh
there's sort of a one angle on this is
just say, um bound your regret on on the
hardware design
uh with as much information as you're
willing to use about generally what I
know about models.
>> Well, one of the areas where
co-design is a is a little bit
contentious is um
the claim that uh you can specialize a
lot for transformers.
>> Mhm.
>> And
maybe even burn in the architecture in
some sense. Um
what do you think of that of the of the
claim that you can get
3x, 10x gains from specializing
specifically for transformers?
>> Pick the grains that you're working on.
Um
large matrix multiplies is a very clear
one. Um
like grain size continues to give you
returns. It they diminish for sure, but
um
uh
if you have lower precision matrix
multiplies, they diminished like they
have diminished less than than if it
were uh
just your
the denominator is larger or it is
smaller and so the the numerator becomes
more important. Um
uh and so I mean like what approach we
take for example is just to say um
matrix multiply and uh and some stuff in
attention is is the place of
specialization, um but like don't take a
whole architecture. Do do appropriate
size pieces.
>> In
uh you know, Ilya's words, right? We're
in the age of research. Um you know,
people are trying all sorts of crazy
stuff.
Um and I feel like 2 3 years ago, if you
saw something that wasn't a transformer,
at least personally, I ignored it.
Um but now I see some of this like weird
stuff and I'm like, "Oh, this is
interesting."
I still don't put much time into it, but
like I I look at at least look at it. Um
and if that's the case, right? You know,
you know, as we move beyond transformers
or at least you should have some as an
as an AI lab, right? If you're not going
to be an AI in Anthropic, GDM, you
should at least have some portion of
your compute into highly flexible uh
compute, right? So so as an example, um
TPUs aren't the best at like
fine-grained like routing and dynamicism
and
um the programming model at least is
pretty painful to do that, especially if
you're just doing research and not like
doing real training or inference, right?
And so you see that with like you know,
doing dynamic stuff with Palace and Jax
and XLA is just a pain in the butt. Um
and on the other hand, like GPUs cuz
they have all these small cores, they're
actually much better at this.
Um and so Google still has some GPUs for
DeepMind. Uh
you think that's like a long-term state
where every lab should have at least
some budget of like, "Hey, screw it.
Let's let's do some like weird wacko
[__] on CPUs too, right? Like
>> I mean, it depends on how much room
there is to optimize. Uh on the one
hand, you can argue that
transformers are kind of a
they're they're a sufficiently general
architecture that they're within a small
constant factor of whatever possible
thing you could possibly think of.
Um
or you could go the other way and be
like
well, the brain has neurons and
something something about the amount of
energy it takes to do something in a
neuron. Um therefore, there's thousand X
gains if we just change the
architecture. And
>> Well, this is what this is what the
brain mouse company is doing, right?
He's He's like He's like doing co-design
from models all the way down to
hardware. Everybody's doing like crazy
analog [__] right?
>> So, if you're in a world where you think
that things are going to happen like
that, you should absolutely be looking
at all this future model research and
really focusing on that. And if you're
thinking that things are going to be
more stable from now on, let's just
focus on
increasing the grain size, uh making
sure that we can really run what we
think is important efficiently.
And not focus so much on these like, I
don't know, 1.2 X, 1.5 X gains where we
could get more from the hardware.
And I don't know which world we're in.
>> I mean, you said Ilya I
I don't know what's on his mind, but
what it sounds like is on his mind is
not necessarily all model architecture.
There's a lot you can do
loss function,
um
training data, and so on.
Or or even just like take a transformer
layer and then who knows, alternate it
with something else. Or uh all of these
things which are available within the um
the world of um
architectures that have like
substantially had some of the fuss of
transformers done at least. Um
uh
>> I I think it's funny by the way you said
you don't know what Ilya is thinking. I
think no one does.
>> Yeah, right.
Yeah.
>> No one
>> If you If you If you look at the like
yeah, of course he does. Um and and
these people do, but I think they're
really close-lipped to the point where
like, you know, SF gossip is usually at
least somewhat okay about people and
companies and things that are happening,
but then like,
you know, I've heard all the way from
like they're making cyber weapons to
like they're just trading financial
markets.
>> And that is.
>> And they're doing everything in between
and all those, yeah.
>> Ilya is
sees very far for sure, but uh
like ultimately comes down to whatever
he ends up shipping.
>> Okay, so so like let's let's take take
yourselves back to like 2022 is it when
he was starting to write internally at
OpenAI about reasoning, right?
Um
which eventually became strawberry and
all these other things, right? Um
you know,
he he tried many many different things
in this direction and finally, I think
it was Yacob figured it out. I'm not
sure if it was him or not.
Um sorry if it was someone else, but you
know, they they figured out like some
form of, you know, test time scaling,
you know, verifiable rewards, you know,
this whole RL pipeline that has now been
sort of giving us crazy gains over the
last
It's actually only been 14 months, by
the way. Really? Since the first
reasoning model.
>> [laughter]
>> Wow, that's been
>> Anyways, uh it's only been like 14
months.
Is there something like,
you know, you know, like if if if
co-design is like, oh well, if you go
back to 2022 everyone was thinking
pre-training era, you know, just keep
scaling pre-training. And now you're
like, wait, actually Ilya was saying in
2022 it's not pre-training. Actually, we
need to we need to co-design for
sampling.
Um what what would do you think like
what do you think about co-design there?
And like what what are your thoughts of
like, hey,
um what would you have done differently
if you're like an Nvidia or someone else
and in 2022 you decided this?
>> Yeah, I think that the challenge there
is that you can always have these
paradigm shifts where suddenly sampling
becomes so much more important
to increasing intelligence in the model.
So, you're no longer doing as much
pre-training. You're now doing
all of these uh uh these decode passes
where your arithmetic intensity is very
low. You need a ton of memory bandwidth.
Suddenly, everything's changed for the
hardware. Um
and
you can't really predict that as a
hardware person.
>> Wait, so if OpenAI made the chip in 2022
when everyone was pre-training building
only Ilya was like, "Let's sample a
reasoning." then the chip would be in
the wrong direction, right?
>> You got to come in with with some amount
of flexibility as to as to where you
think things are going to go. And like
at the time like Ilya was the only
person who's up this. Eventually, it was
two people, three people. And then
eventually, suddenly the whole company
and the whole industry.
>> I think the labs have to hedge in this
way. Like and I mean they have to hedge
across different hardwares
as a result. I think sort of the
incentives for hardware vendors are
maybe different in that
um
and and it really depends whether you're
Nvidia where you can't fail. You have to
make a generalist product like your next
generation Nvidia product has to sell.
>> Well, no, but they're they're making
three products now, right? They're doing
the they're doing the main line. They're
doing the CPX, right? High arithmetic
intensity. They're doing the like the
Groq stuff, right? With it's like a You
know, they're doing the 3D DRAM instead
of like SRAM, but like you know,
they're making different bets.
>> That's Yeah, but there's some amount of
that. So, if you can make multiple
products, that's another way to hedge
for sure. Um most companies that aren't
Nvidia or maybe Google
um
can't spin off multiple products uh
simultaneously. So, I mean I think the
right thing that like for for companies
that are making that choice is just like
make the best guess and try. Um I think
like if your best guess is
like as making hardware trying to hedge
across all all possible scenarios, um
you just don't win. Um like you don't
win any in any of the scenarios. Um
you totally can as a lab because you can
wait and see and and decide which one to
buy. But but as a as a hardware vendor,
you have to make some some some effort
for sure.
>> So so I guess I guess I'm curious of
your two perspectives, right? Like
you know, Cerebras, Groq, they were
working on something that
and and they were not focused on the
low-latency sampling regime, I don't
think. Um Yeah, I think similar
>> It seems like they kind of fell into
that accidentally, where they were
>> it's now a co-design point that actually
makes it
>> Exactly, exactly. They it it worked out
so well because they were working on
these ConfNets that were very small and
could fit entirely on
>> The other picture here is it's LSTMs
that were also like very
>> uh small, very very uh sequential.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, and so so you can fit that all
into one tile. Same thing for for for
Dojo as well. Uh and then suddenly LLMs
come along. It actually turns out you do
need to be able to have like terabytes
of parameters now. Uh
and that's a very different regime, but
in this specific market where you really
really care about low latency above all
else, like like encoding
uh like in quite a few um
of these like thinking models would just
just take too long. Um
this actually really matters and this is
a really good niche for them to be in.
>> So, I mean my take at least on on on the
low-latency thing is uh I mean, if you
look at what that means, you are
um I mean, you want low latency, for
sure. Uh and SRAM is really the only
only strategy to get there. Maybe the 3D
stacked DRAM is is um isn't a perfect
way to get it close to that. Um it's
it's interesting for other reasons, like
KB hash. Um But then, what do you do
with all of that compute? Like you made
a you've made a product that has a lot
of compute because of the other use
cases for prefill and training and so
on. Um
and I mean, if you look at lab pricing,
it kind of looks like the fact just the
fact that prefill tokens are I don't
know, five times cheaper than decode
tokens
says something about what utilization or
efficiency is in prefill versus decode.
That probably means that during decode
you have a whole bunch of compute
sitting idle.
I think like the biggest uh research
agenda for taking advantage of that is
to say, "Hey, can I take a model and
uh make uh the um the MLP much bigger?"
And somehow use those spare flops. Like
80% of your flops are sitting idle.
Do anything at all it must be better
than doing nothing and and and take
advantage of that. Um
I mean, simplest thing to do is just
crank up the MLP size by a factor of
five and and take advantage of that.
>> We're in an age where you see a lot of
disaggregation, right? Um people are
doing uh disaggregation of prefill and
decode. Initially, they were doing on
the same chips. Um doing things like
chunk prefill as well. Anything to
anything to sort of like get utilization
up higher. Uh then they started doing
disaggregated prefill decode on
different kinds of chips, right? Um at
least that's what's Nvidia's pitch
today.
Um
and then they're sort of like we we you
know, we've at least built our own
shitty simulator which is probably
internally which probably worse than
yours and worse than yours. Um but at
least it's like given us some ideas on
like, "Hey, actually you would want to
You may want to disaggregate the MLP
from the attention even, right?" And MLP
you could have the weights in let's say
SRAM or 3D RAM and the attention you
want through HPM. And this is something
that we've also like sort of like I
guess
what where do you do you see this wave
cuz you're both you know, you're making
one chip, right? Like at least uh my
understanding is you're making one chip.
Um there's a wave of like different
optimization points for prefill and
decode. Um
you know, say if in a sampling heavy
regime versus in a regime where you're
doing a lot of backwards passes. Um
>> Yeah, I I think I think it's really cool
to think about decoupling uh where for
example, sparse uh sparse MLPs where you
suddenly are decoupling your the amount
of math you have to do and the amount of
a kind of effective model capacity for
knowledge. Um and this really affects
the hardware in a lot of ways because
now you're not you're not tied together
like that anymore. Now, you can
have much less arithmetic intensity for
the same amount of HBM, uh same amount
of HBM bandwidth uh for reading in the
parameters. And so, decoupling the
attention in the the MLP is very
interesting because these are very
different operations. Uh and if you do
put these on different devices,
uh maybe even like totally different
memory technologies even, uh like you're
suggesting, I think you can have a lot
of wins.
Uh
it is
maybe a little bit scary from the
software perspective. Uh
now, you have to coordinate two
different types of devices.
Um
Who knows what's going to happen there?
>> Some of the like this the thing that
makes it scary is you have to decide um
somewhat a a priori of uh how many
resources are going on this side and how
many resources resources going on that
side. That's true. Um
and so, uh that ends up baking in this
is going to be my ratio of attention to
MLP or to MLW or something like that. Um
and I mean, we we we make those
decisions all the time. We pick on
resource balances between memories and
and and compute and so on. Um this is
one more of them. Um and it's sort of
like uh
and sort of doubling all the decisions I
make I make all the decisions on the
left and then I make all the decisions
on the right.
To some ex- and and then I guess the
other thing that you can get like if the
the trade-off is also removes your
ability to steal um dynamically uh like
uh uh re- steal resources between
attention and and and and and Emily. So,
uh a classic thing is to um be fetching
always be fetching KBs from HBM um even
while you're running the MLE. Um
uh and and then use a little bit of the
HBM bandwidth to fetch weights or
something as up like that as well. Um
and so, uh sliding where that that that
divider is is is something you can do on
a single chip and it's difficult to do
on multiple chips. As the workloads
become more expensive for sure, like the
um
just find every little part and make the
the thing you can for those little
parts. Seems like a long time trend.
It's just like when is the right time is
is is the question.
>> So, one of my pet peeves in quantization
papers is that
uh they come out with a claim that says
we're 97% as accurate as
uh as the full thing. And turns out if
you look into the numbers, actually this
is like downgrading a 70 billion model
to an 8 billion model.
Um, how do you think about this?
>> Yeah, what what does accurate even mean,
right? Like you take perplexity and it's
like
one over 97% of perplexity or something
like that. Or like 97% uh MMLU score or
something like that. Yeah.
>> I It's It's 97% of the MMLU score once
you did post-quantization
training. You know, that's usually what
they do.
>> Like you see these companies advertising
like these 0.1%
differences on these
uh on these evals.
>> So, I mean, the problem behind this,
right, is the
um
>> Actually, I don't know if it's a
logarithmic relationship between amount
of compute and and like perplexity
improvement or something like that.
Uh so,
so that's what gives you all of this
sensitivity to those small things.
Um,
why not just hit the same quality with
more model parameters? That seems a much
fairer way. So, um
I think that it should be a standard for
how how
how you do these things. We
in general, we find that we need to
increase the model size by a 40% in
order to hit the same quality level. Um,
a better paper would be 35% instead of
40%.
>> Yeah, makes sense.
The way I like to frame it is perplexity
per picojoule.
Where
if you are the same perplexity,
how many picojoules how much energy did
you take to generate this token?
>> Per picojoule. So, if I have twice as
many picojoules, I get twice the
perplexity?
>> That's not literally division. It's a
There's a predo there.
>> Okay.
>> What is it your license plate? Can you
tell us your license plate?
>> It's exaflop.
>> It's exaflop. Oh, I thought it was like
intelligence per picojoule or something
like this.
PJ p e r o p picojoules per op is open.
It is open source. Oh, wow.
PJ per p per bit, too, would be pretty
good, but that is that's too many
letters, eh?